Irving R. Kaufman Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Irving R. Kaufman Papers 1934-1992 1949-1992
MSS81576
Kaufman, Irving R. (Irving Robert), 1910-1992
43,000 items
144 containers plus 3 oversize
58.7 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Jurist. Court papers, office and subject files, speeches and writings, and scrapbooks chiefly documenting Kaufman's judicial career on the United States District Court, Southern District of New York and United States Court of Appeals, Second Circuit.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bonanno, Joseph, 1905-2002--Trials, litigation, etc.; Burger, Warren E., 1907-1995--Correspondence.; Clark, Tom C. (Tom Campbell), 1899-1977--Correspondence.; Kaufman, Irving R. (Irving Robert), 1910-1992.; Rifkind, Simon H. (Simon Hirsch), 1901-1995--Correspondence.; Rosenberg, Ethel, 1915-1953--Trials, litigation, etc.; Rosenberg, Julius, 1918-1953--Trials, litigation, etc.
Organizations
American Bar Association.; Juvenile Justice Standards Project.; New Rochelle (N.Y.). Board of Education--Trials, litigation, etc.; United States. Court of Appeals (2nd Circuit); United States. District Court (New York: Southern District)
Subjects
Appellate courts--United States.; District courts--New York (State); Judicial opinions--United States.; Juvenile justice, Administration of--United States.; Law--United States.; Mafia trials--United States.; Segregation in education--New York (State)--New Rochelle.; Trials (Espionage)--United States.
Occupations
Judges.; Lawyers.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Irving R. Kaufman, jurist, were given to the Library of Congress in 1992 by Helen R. Kaufman, Stephen E. Banner, and Robert J. Katz.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Irving R. Kaufman are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1910, June 24 Born, New York, N.Y.
1931 LL.B., Fordham University, New York, N.Y.
1932 Admitted to New York Bar
1932 1935 Private practice, New York, N.Y.
1935 1939 Special assistant to United States attorney, Southern District of New York
1936 Married Helen Ruth Rosenberg
1939 1940 Assistant United States attorney, Southern District of New York
1940 1949 Partner, Noonan, Kaufman & Eagan, New York, N.Y.
1947 1948 Special assistant to United States attorney general in charge of lobbying investigation
1949 1961 Judge, United States District Court, Southern District of New York
1961 1987 Judge, United States Court of Appeals, Second Circuit
1973 1980 Chief judge, United States Court of Appeals, Second Circuit
1987 1992 Senior judge, United States Court of Appeals, Second Circuit
1987 Awarded Presidential Medal of Freedom
1992, Feb. 1 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Irving Robert Kaufman (1910-1992) span the years 1934-1992 with the vast bulk of material dating after 1949, when Kaufman was appointed to the federal judiciary. The papers document his professional activities while serving for over forty years as a federal judge, first as a district judge and then as an appellate judge for the second circuit. Included are speeches and writings, correspondence, scrapbooks, material from American Bar Association committees that Kaufman chaired or served on, items from the Juvenile Justice Standards Project which he chaired, conference materials, court papers, and subject files. Personal and family papers are few.
The first two series are comprised of papers from Kaufman's two judgeships: the Southern District of New York (1949-1961) and the Second Circuit Court of Appeals (1961-1992). Each series is divided into two subseries: Court Papers and Office Files. The Court Papers from the Southern District of New York include transcripts of testimony, charges to juries, opinions, sentences, and appeals. Fourteen of Kaufman's district court cases appear in the Case Files, including two of his most famous and controversial cases: United States v. Rosenberg (1951 espionage trial of Julius and Ethel Rosenberg) and United States v. Bonanno (1959 trial of reputed gangsters who had met in Apalachin, New York). Materials related to these and other cases are also in the scrapbooks, the final series in the papers. Additional material concerning United States v. Rosenberg is under the case name in a Subject File. The Office Files for the Southern District of New York are quite small and consist of material from professional organizations, committees, conferences, and seminars. A collection of speeches, mostly written by others and used as a reference file by Kaufman, relate in large part to communism.
The Court Papers of the second series, the Second Circuit Court of Appeals, are very few. The two case files present are composed primarily of memoranda between the judges. Also included are affirmances, dockets, and opinions. The extensive Office Files subseries for the Court of Appeals is comprised of Kaufman's papers from American Bar Association committees, the Juvenile Justice Standards Program, professional organizations, conferences and seminars, materials concerning the operation of the courthouse and the courts of the second circuit, reference papers, and correspondence with other judges. There is substantial correspondence between Kaufman and Supreme Court Chief Justice Warren E. Burger and Justice Tom C. Clark.
The Subject File contains most of Kaufman's correspondence with various individuals. Substantial correspondence is present between Kaufman and his longtime friend Simon H. Rifkind. There are also files on the Harvard Law School fellowship named in Kaufman's honor, the Presidential Medal of Freedom bestowed on Kaufman, several law schools, news clippings, nonprofessional organizations, and topics of interest to Kaufman, such as drug abuse and cameras in the courtroom.
Kaufman's prolific writing was aided by his law clerks, as memoranda to them indicate. He published widely and delivered many speeches. The Speeches and Writings series has been split into several chronologically arranged sections: articles, book reviews, letters to the editor, research material, and speeches. Correspondence with publishers, readers, or event organizers is often included.
The final series is a set of three scrapbooks dating from 1951 to 1970. The books are filled with news clippings, most dating from Kaufman's service on the district court. The first volume and part of the second are devoted to the Rosenbergs' trial, appeals, and execution. With the help of a clipping service, Kaufman assembled items from many diverse sources. Other cases highlighted in the scrapbooks are United States v. Bonanno and Taylor v. Board of Education, the 1961 school desegregation case from New Rochelle, New York.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in six series:
United States District Court, Southern District of New York, 1934-1968
United States Court of Appeals, Second Circuit, 1942-1992
Subject File, 1945-1992
Speeches and Writings, 1945-1991
Formerly Restricted, 1976-1978
Scrapbooks (Oversize), 1951-1970
Container List
- United States District Court, Southern District of New York, 1934-1968 (Box 1-30)
  - Court Papers, 1949-1963 (Box 1-24)
    Case files, appeals, opinions, and sentences.
    Arranged chronologically by type of material.
    - Appeals (Box 1)
      - Index, 1949-1963
      - A-Z, 1949-1963, (4 folders)
    - Case files (Box 2)
      - 1951
        - Compania Punta Alta v. Dalzell Towing Co., (2 folders)
        - United States v. Rosenberg
          - Vol. 1
          - Vol. 2 (Box 3)
          - Vol. 3 (Box 4)
        - Van Der Horst Corp. v. Chromium Corp., (2 folders); (5 folders); (1 folder) (Box 5, Box 6)
      - 1952
        - Helene Curtis Indus. v. Sales Affiliates
        - Portman v. American Home Products, (3 folders)
        - In re Third Avenue Transit, (3 folders) (Box 7)
      - 1953
        - Naamloze Vennootschap Suikerfabriek v. Chase Nat'l Bank, (2 folders); (3 folders) (Box 8)
      - 1956, In re Andrea Doria
      - 1957, Zoomar, Inc. v. Paillard Products, (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - 1958, United States v. Stromberg, (3 folders)
      - 1959 (Box 10)
        - Cott Beverage v. Canada Dry
        - United States v. Bonanno
          - Chronology
          - Minutes (incomplete)
          - Testimony
            - Coconspirators and defendants not on trial, (4 folders)
            - Defendants, (1 folder); (2 folders) (Box 11)
            - Witnesses, (3 folders)
        - United States v. United Scenic Artists Local 829
      - 1960, United States v. Lever Bros.
    - Cases decided (Box 12)
      - 7 Nov. 1949-20 Aug. 1952, (2 vols.)
      - 9 Sept. 1952-14 Nov. 1957, (2 vols.) (Box 13)
      - 4 Dec. 1957-27 Dec. 1960 (Box 14)
    - Civil charges
      - Index, undated
      - A-G, 1950-1961, (2 folders)
      - I-W, 1950-1961, undated, (3 folders) (Box 15)
    - Criminal charges
      - Index, undated
      - A-J, 1950-1959, (2 folders)
      - L-W, 1950-1959, (5 folders) (Box 16)
    - Opinions (Box 17)
      - Index, undated
      - 9 Nov. 1949-29 May 1950, (4 folders)
      - 1 June 1950-21 Jan. 1952, (6 folders) (Box 18)
      - 15 Feb. 1952-9 April 1953, (6 folders) (Box 19)
      - 13 April 1953-27 April 1955, (6 folders) (Box 20)
      - 3 May 1955-12 Nov. 1957, (5 folders) (Box 21)
      - 12 Nov. 1957-17 June 1959, (6 folders) (Box 22)
      - 9 June 1959-31 May 1961, (6 folders) (Box 23)
    - Sentences, 1951-1963, (2 folders) (Box 24)
  - Office Files, 1934-1968 (Box 24-30)
    Correspondence, notebooks from meetings and conferences, a compilation of speeches and essays used as a reference file, and miscellaneous material.
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - Admiralty rules, 1952, 1960 (Box 24)
    - Advisory Council of Judges-National Council on Crime and Delinquency
      - Correspondence, 1959-1960
      - Miscellany, 1960-1961
    - American Bar Association, circa 1956-1960
    - American Judicature Society, 1952-1960
    - Association of the Bar of the City of New York, 1957-1960
    - Calendar rules, 1955
    - Committees
      - Administration of Criminal Law
        - Levet, Richard H., 1961
        - Notebook I, 1960, (1 folder); (2 folders) (Box 25)
        - Notebook II, 1961
        - Notebook III, 1961, (2 folders)
      - Inter-Circuit Assignments, 1960
      - Motion Procedure, 1960-1961, (2 folders)
      - Pretrial, 1953-1961
    - Criminal law notes, undated (Box 26)
    - Federal Bar Association, 1949-1960
    - Glossary of legal terms and words, undated
    - Judges
      - Biggs, John, 1960-1961
      - Estes, Joe Ewing, 1961
      - Ryan, Sylvester J., 1960-1961
      - Warren, Earl, 1960
    - Judicial Conferences
      - Second Circuit, Manchester, Vt., 1960
      - United States, Washington, D.C., 1960
    - Legislation
      - Division of business among district judges, 1959-1960
      - United States voting referees, 1960
      - Youth Corrections Act, 1960
    - Miscellany, 1955-1962
    - New York County Lawyers' Association, 1953-1960, undated
    - New York State Bar Association, 1951-1961
    - Pilot Institute on Sentencing, Boulder, Colo.
      - Desk book, 1959, (2 folders)
      - Miscellany, 1952-1960, undated
    - Points of law, undated, (2 folders) (Box 27)
    - Seminar on protracted cases, Palo Alto, Calif., 1958-1959
    - Speeches and essays
      - Set A, 1939-1955, (4 folders)
      - Set B, notebooks (Box 28)
        - Communism, 1950-1960, undated, (3 folders)
        - Miscellaneous
          - A-C, 1944-1961, undated, (4 folders)
          - D-F, 1949-1958, undated, (3 folders) (Box 29)
          - G-L, 1949-1962, 1968, undated, (4 folders)
          - M-Z, 1934, 1950-1959, undated, (4 folders) (Box 30)
- United States Court of Appeals, Second Circuit, 1942-1992 (Box 30-115)
  - Court Papers, 1961-1992 (Box 30-34)
    Affirmances, case files, dockets, and opinions.
    Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
    - Affirmances from bench (Box 30)
      - No opinion, 1964-1973, (2 folders)
      - With opinion, 1965-1971
      - Written opinions not published, 1964-1969
    - Case files See Container 144, Formerly Restricted
      - Sept. term 1975, Buckley v. Littell, 1976-1977
      - Sept. term 1977, Turpin v. Mailet, 1977-1978, undated
    - Dockets (Box 31)
      - Index, 1961-1985, (6 folders)
      - Oct. 1961-Dec. 1977, (13 folders) (Box 32)
      - Jan. 1978-June 1990, (10 folders) (Box 33)
      - Sept. 1990-Jan. 1992 (Box 34)
    - Miscellany, 1978-1982, 1990
    - Opinions
      - Miscellaneous, 1969, 1980-1982
      - Notebook, 1963-1971, (2 folders)
  - Office Files, 1942-1992 (Box 34-115)
    Correspondence, conference material, notebooks, reports, news clippings, photographs, and miscellaneous material.
    - Absence memoranda, 1962-1983, undated, 1963-1971; (4 folders) (Box 34)
    - Administrative Office of the United States Courts
      - 1961-1985, (2 folders)
      - 1986-1991, undated (Box 35)
    - Administrative services, Foley Square courthouse, New York, N.Y., 1977-1980, 1988-1989
    - Advisory Council of Judges, National Council on Crime and Delinquency
      - Correspondence, 1961-1963
      - Juvenile and family courts section, 1961
      - Law of Criminal Correction, undated, (2 folders)
      - Meetings, 1962-1963
      - Miscellany, 1961-1963, undated (Box 36)
      - Memoranda, 1961-1963
      - Model Sentencing Act, 1961-1962, undated
    - American Arbitration Association, 1987
    - American Bar Association
      - Annual Meetings
        - 1972, San Francisco, Calif., prayer breakfast, 1972
        - 1974, Honolulu, Hawaii, 1973-1974
        - 1975, Montreal, Canada, 1975
        - 1976, Atlanta, Ga., 1975-1976
        - 1978, New York, N.Y., 1977-1978
        - 1985, London, England, 1985, undated
        - 1986, New York, N.Y., 1986
        - 1988, Toronto, Canada, 1988, undated
        - 1989, Honolulu, Hawaii, 1988-1989
      - Commission on federal judicial compensation, 1984, undated (Box 37)
      - Correspondence, 1966-1991, (5 folders)
      - Journal correspondence, 1977-1991, undated
      - Judges' Journal, 1964-1971
      - Judicial administration section, 1968-1980
      - Miscellany, 1967-1980, undated (Box 38)
      - Presidential showcase program, 1983
    - American College of Trial Lawyers
      - Annual meetings and preconference seminars
        - 1985, London, England, and Paris, France, 1985
        - 1986, New York, N.Y., 1986
      - Correspondence, 1970-1991, (3 folders)
      - Fair Jury, 1966-1967
      - Miscellany, 1967, 1977-1978, undated
    - American Inns of Court Foundation, 1991
    - American Judicature Society, 1962-1991
    - American Law Institute, Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 39)
      - Annual meeting, 1974
      - Correspondence, 1962-1991, (3 folders)
    - Anglo-American Legal Exchange
      - Conferences, 1969-1980, (3 folders)
      - Correspondence
        - 1969-1976, (2 folders)
        - 1977-1984, (6 folders) (Box 40)
      - Miscellany, 1976-1981, undated
      - News clippings, 1972-1983, undated
      - Participants, undated
      - Reports, 1977, undated
      - Writings, 1948, 1976-1977, undated (Box 41)
    - Annual reports for the Second Circuit, 1977-1983, (4 folders)
    - Appeals to the Second Circuit, 1970
    - Appellate judges seminars, 1988-1989
    - Association of the Bar of the City of New York
      - Committee on Federal Courts
      - Correspondence, 1961-1989, (3 folders)
      - Miscellany, 1971-1982, undated
      - National moot court competition, 1973-1978, (4 folders) (Box 42)
      - Notices of meetings and lectures, 1973-1988
      - Reports, 1965, 1977-1980, undated
    - Audit report, 1983
    - Authority for recurrent points of law
      - Vol. I, circa 1966, (2 folders)
      - Vol. II, circa 1972, (3 folders)
    - Bicentennial conference of judges of the United States Courts of Appeals, 1988 (Box 43)
    - Bicentennial of the United States constitution, 1986-1987
    - Birthday celebrations, 1981-1991
    - California Supreme Court, 1965
    - Case assignment by screening, 1973
    - Case loads
      - Correspondence, 1968-1981, undated, (2 folders)
      - Miscellany, 1971-1976, undated
      - Special session for the second circuit, 1978
    - Certification as senior judge, 1990-1992
    - Chief judges meetings, 1969, 1980
    - Civil appeals management plan (CAMP)
      - Correspondence, 1976-1991
      - Evaluation, 1980-1981
      - Miscellany, 1976-1983, undated (Box 44)
      - Yale Law Journal, 1985-1986
    - Committees
      - Administration of the Criminal Law
        - Legislation, 1968
        - Meetings
          - Miscellaneous, 1964-1968, (3 folders)
          - Notebooks
            - 1962-1964, (4 folders)
            - 1965-1968, (4 folders) (Box 45)
      - Advisory Committee of Planning for the District Courts, undated
      - Business Committee for Court Administration, 1970-1971
      - Code of Judicial Conduct, 1973-1974 (Box 46)
      - Fair Trial and Free Press, 1968-1972
      - Judicial Activities, 1970-1974, undated
      - Judicial Branch
        - Correspondence
          - Jan. 1979-Sept. 1980, (5 folders)
          - Oct. 1980-Apr. 1981, (6 folders) (Box 47)
          - May 1981-Aug. 1982, (5 folders) (Box 48)
          - Sept. 1982-June 1984, (4 folders) (Box 49)
        - Legislation
          - Nov. 1978-Sept. 1981, (3 folders)
          - Oct. 1981-Feb. 1985, undated (Box 50)
        - Litigation, 1979-1981, (2 folders)
        - Meetings, 1980-1983, undated, (2 folders)
        - Membership, 1980, undated
        - Miscellany, 1979-1980, undated (Box 51)
        - Mission statement, 1982, undated
        - News clippings
          - 1979-1980, (5 folders)
          - 1981-1989, undated, (2 folders) (Box 52)
        - Notes, undated
        - Reports, 1977-1983, undated, (4 folders)
        - Speeches and statements, 1976-1983, undated, (4 folders) (Box 53)
        - Statistics, 1980-1982
      - Operation of the Jury System
        - American Bar Foundation
          - Correspondence, 1967-1969
          - Report, 1968
        - "Automation of Jury Clerical Work in United States District Courts," 1969 (Box 54)
        - Cases, 1966-1968, undated, (2 folders)
        - Correspondence, 1966-1972, (3 folders)
        - "Guidelines to Assist District Courts in Conforming to the Jury Selection and Service Act of 1968," 1968 (Box 55)
        - Guidelines for Improving Juror Utilization in United States District Courts, 1972
        - Joint study group on jury trials in criminal cases, 1971-1972
        - Juries of less than twelve, 1971
        - Legislation, 1967-1971, undated, (4 folders)
        - Meetings
          - 1966
          - 1967, (6 folders) (Box 56)
          - 1968-1972, (8 folders) (Box 57)
          - 1973, (2 folders) (Box 58)
        - Membership, 1966-1972
        - Miscellany, 1968-1972, undated
        - News clippings, 1967-1972, undated
        - Reports
          - 1942, 1967-1972, (4 folders)
          - 1973, (3 folders) (Box 59)
        - Rule 24 (c), Federal rules of criminal procedure
          - 1972-1973
        - Testimony, 1967
      - Pretrial Procedure (Box 60)
        - Correspondence, 1961-1968, (2 folders)
        - "Handbook of Effective Pretrial Procedure," 1964
        - Meetings
          - Aug. 1962, 1962
          - July 1963
            - Correspondence, 1963
            - General, 1963, (2 folders)
            - Notebook, 1963 (Box 61)
          - Aug. 1964
            - Correspondence, 1964-1965
            - Notebook, 1964
          - July 1965
            - Correspondence, 1964-1965
            - Notebook, 1965
          - Aug. 1966, 1966
          - July 1967
            - Correspondence, 1967
            - General, 1967
            - Notebook, 1967 (Box 62)
          - July 1968, 1968
        - Miscellany, 1963-1968
        - "Outline of Suggested Procedures and Materials for Pre-Trial and Trial of Complex and Multiple Litigation," undated
        - Subcommittees
          - Multiple Litigation, 1965-1967
          - Pretrial of Criminal Cases, 1963-1966, (2 folders)
          - To Consider a Possible Revision of Rule 16, 1963-1964 (Box 63)
          - To Draft a Statement of the Essentials of Pretrial Procedure, 1963-1964, undated
      - Sentencing Practices
        - Correspondence, 1972-1984, (6 folders)
        - Military sentencing, 1970-1973, undated
        - Miscellany, 1973-1977, undated
        - News clippings, 1973-1979, undated (Box 64)
        - Presentence reports, 1974
        - Press releases, 1973-1979
        - Reports, 1974-1975, undated
      - Standards of Judicial Conduct
        - Background material, 1970
        - Meetings
          - Jan.-Oct. 1970, (4 folders)
          - Dec. 1970-Aug. 1972, (5 folders) (Box 65)
        - News clippings, 1972
        - Notebook, 1970-1975, (2 folders) (Box 66)
        - Reporter's Notes to Code of Judicial Conduct, 1972-1973, (2 folders)
    - Congress
      - Federal Courts Improvement Act, 1979
      - Federal habeas corpus, 1965-1966
      - Legislative proposals to limit judicial authority, 1982
      - Senate Judiciary Committee, 1960-1963
    - Correctional Association of New York, 1962
    - Court administration, 1973-1975
    - Criminal Justice Act (Box 67)
      - Correspondence, 1963-1972, undated, (3 folders)
      - Miscellany, 1963-1972, undated
      - Plans
        - Districts
          - Connecticut, 1965-1976
          - Eastern New York, 1964-1971, undated
          - Northern New York, 1965-1971, undated
          - Southern New York, 1965-1971
          - Vermont, 1964-1971 (Box 68)
          - Western New York, 1965-1971, undated
        - Miscellaneous, 1964
        - Second Circuit, 1964-1972, undated, (2 folders)
    - Criminal trials, 1964-1965, 1971-1972
    - Designations, 1972, undated
    - Discovery rules, 1962, 1977-1983
    - Districts
      - Connecticut
        - Bridgeport courthouse, 1975-1976
        - Miscellany, 1976-1982
      - Southern Florida, 1982
      - Southern New York (Box 69)
        - Correspondence, 1973-1984, undated
        - Court plan, 1983
        - Liaison committee, 1973-1974, undated
        - News clippings, 1974-1975, undated
      - Vermont, 1977-1983
      - Western New York, 1978-1983
    - Evidence, federal rules of, 1973-1979
    - Federal Administrative Law Judges Conference, 1981
    - Federal Bar Association
      - Correspondence, 1961-1973
      - Miscellany, 1961-1962, 1967-1978, undated
    - Federal Bar Council
      - Correspondence, 1969-1991
      - Distinguished judicial service award, 1986 (Box 70)
      - Judicial salaries, 1964, 1969-1976
      - Miscellany, 1971-1974, 1985, undated
    - Federal Defender Services Unit, 1973-1980, (3 folders)
    - Federal Judges Association, 1981-1984
    - Federal Judicial Center
      - Advisory Committee on Continuing Education
        - Correspondence, 1968-1970, (3 folders)
        - Meetings, 1968-1970
        - Miscellany, 1968, undated
        - Reports, 1965-1969 (Box 71)
      - Appellate judges' conferences/seminars
        - Nov. 1972, Washington, D.C., 1972
        - Mar. 1973, Washington, D.C., 1972-1973
        - Oct. 1976, Phoenix, Ariz., 1976, undated
      - Establishment of, 1967-1968, (2 folders)
      - General correspondence
        - 1967-1970, (2 folders)
        - 1971-1989, (2 folders) (Box 72)
      - Miscellany, 1968-1986, undated
      - Reports
        - Annual and midyear, 1968-1980, (2 folders)
        - Miscellaneous, 1968-1974